Chapter 1: Summer Job

Author's Note: this "story" is actually a collection of "flashes" set in the months and years following the main events of Following the Phoenix. If you have not yet read the main story, this will not make much sense. Following the Phoenix can be found under my pen name (hezzel), then go to My Stories. Or directly skip to s/10636246/1/

Please note: I am not actively developing this story anymore, just writing the occasional chapter because I enjoy writing and some of these ideas stuck in my mind. Flashes has no true plot, and some of the flashes are likely to be less interesting than others. I guess what I'm saying is: please don't feel obliged to read this even if you did enjoy FtP. :) Also, please do not expect regular updates; I will probably keep posting now and then, but there will be large hiatuses.

For those who have spent the past few months reading many HPMOR-sequel-fanfics: remember that FtP is not a sequel, it's a spinoff, which does not include the final arc of HPMOR. In FtP, souls exist, Harry Potter is just Harry Potter, and his pet rock simply died due to negligence. At the end of the story, Hermione has a phoenix, the statute of secrecy has fallen and Harry has gained a new mentor.

July 1992.

Hermione loved her parents. That much was really beyond question. And she was thrilled that, after all the changes the last months had brought, she could finally involve them in her world, showing them all the wonders of magic and the culture surrounding it. However, she had to admit that certain things had been significantly more practical when magic was secret, the Hogwarts staff operated on a need-to-know basis with respect to Muggle parens, and she was able to carefully refrain from telling them anything that would particularly worry them.

The permission form lay on the table between them. She was a minor, after all, and needed parental permission for a summer job, especially a potentially hazardous one, no matter what she may have been up to in the previous months.

"Hermione is twelve," her father said in a strained voice. "Don't you have adults who can do this work?"

"Frankly, no," the man from the British Space Agency said calmly. "There aren't that many people with a phoenix in the world, and most of them are too old, too busy, or don't understand the first thing about technology. What's more, none of them are ours – British citizens – except for one old man who has neither the time nor the inclination."

"It's not safe," her mother protested.

"Actually, there's no reason to expect any danger," the man contradicted her. "We're aware of her youth, and won't lightly assign her any hazardous missions. Her tasks will be primarily research-related – for example, we'd like to test the speed of a phoenix, and whether it's subject to relativity. If we send her into space – and rest assured that you'll have to agree on every individual mission of such a nature – it'll be done with all possible precautions. For example, before even thinking of allowing Hermione to go to the moon, we'd send an older witch or wizard there in the usual way to verify that the conditions are no problem to magic users. We'd also confirm beforehand that magical creatures can survive, and have a rocket with trained astronauts near the place where she would arrive, just in case. She could be returned the normal way if the phoenix should fail her."

"Or you could take her to a satellite first?" Her father brought up.

"Right," the man nodded calmly. "Although that might actually be less safe, since magic is apparently known to disturb electrical devices. That's actually another test we'd like to perform soon – how much and what kind of magic our devices can handle, and whether the conditions of outer space affect this."

Hermione looked from her father to her mother. "Pleeeeaaaase?"

Mother frowned deeply. "Herm, dear, do you know how many space missions have gone wrong? Real life isn't like the movies, quite a few astronauts have died!"

"It's not the same!" She argued. "I'll have Xare with me, and people protecting me and magical shielding and everything. Plus, you heard Mr. Town, it'll mostly be about research, all on earth."

"In the beginning, perhaps," her mother said sharply. "But I expect we'll be seeing quite a few more forms before the year is over!"

"Mum," she begged. "Please? I really want to do this, and I think it needs to be done. It could mean so much for everyone... there's so much we could learn! And it honestly doesn't seem all that dangerous." Xare rubbed her beak against Hermione's cheek in support, and agreed with a loud "Caw!".

Her parents just gave each other a long look.

"Mr. Town," her father asked. "Do you mind if my wife and I discuss in private for a few moments?"

"Not at all. I can return later, if you prefer."

"Just a few minutes." The two disappeared into the kitchen.

Hermione bit her lip. Unfortunately, this really was her parents' decision, and aside from putting on her most convincing pleading, there wasn't all that much she could do about it. And yes, in all fairness, even with the BSA being very careful, there probably would be a little bit more danger than a twelve-year-old child was generally exposed to in the Muggle world. It was just that, after everything that had been going on for the past year, her sense of danger had been recalibrated a bit. Anything the adults in the British Space Agency were likely to allow a girl her age to do was probably not much more dangerous than the average flying lesson in Hogwarts. After facing the Wizengamot twice, all her escapades in Azkaban, hopping over the world destroying Dementors, being lethally shot and evacuating people in the middle of a battle to the death, she just couldn't be afraid of merely doing magical research in outer space. Besides, with Xare by her side, she was doomed to get into hazardous situations anyway.

The door opened and her parents returned. There was a tense silence, before her father broke it.

"Hermione," he began, in a grave tone. Her heart sank. Of the two, he had been the one who seemed more positive about the possible adventure. "I hope you understand our concerns. Just a few weeks ago we learned that, despite everything your Professor McGonagall told us about Hogwarts being safe, you ended up being framed for murder, judged as an adult, and thrown into a rather horrifying prison – which we had to learn about from the television."

Hermione squirmed. There had been words about that, although her parents had at last accepted that at the time she had had good reasons to postpone the inevitable confrontation.

"We would never go behind your back, sir," Mr. Town assured him.

"I know, I know," father sighed. "It's just that... after that, and then the sudden war, you can probably see why we're a little worried about assurances of safety. Really, we want nothing more than to keep our little girl close to us, wrap her up in cotton wool and keep her away from anything dangerous for the rest of her life."

"But you can't, Dad," Hermione argued. "There's always going to be some dangers. And it doesn't seem like it would be that bad in this case, while there's a lot of good that I could do with the space program."

"We know, honey," her mother agreed quietly, glancing at Xare. "And we know that you're never going to have a normal childhood no matter what we say." She grimaced sadly.

Her father cleared his throat. "All things considered, you're probably right. In comparison to some of the things you've been up to this year, going to the moon seems positively mundane. And that's not even what your main work will be for the time being." He looked at the BSA man, who nodded calmly.

"So... you'll let me go?" Hermione hardly dared to ask it.

"Let's get this straight: we want good reassurances, we want to be kept fully into the loop, we will look over everything that requires our permission, we want to be able to end or suspend your contract at any time, and we'd like some words with the magical government about additional protections they can give you. But conditional on that... yes, we'll allow it."

As Hermione squealed and jumped to hug her parents, the phoenix cawed a rousing battle cry.

Chapter 5: Transfiguring Energy

"All right," Dr. Madelaine Deyne summarized. "Transfiguration is not permanent. I get that. But that's really the only danger?"

"Oh no, certainly not," the middle-aged wizard who had introduced himself as Master Blake protested. "But it's the main one. Problems like instability only tend to occur during experiments."

Dr. Deyne frowned. "Right. So how does this work at the molecular level? If you transfigure a block of ice into wood and burn – yes, I know you shouldn't do that, but hypothetically – would you get water vapor? Hydrogen? Or even hydroxide or hydronium, or odd bindings that would never occur in nature?"

Master Blake shifted uncomfortably. "This is getting into theoretical transfiguration. You know our mandate is only to look for practical applications – there's a moratorium on any foundational study until enough experts on both sides have been cleared to perform such a study in a responsible way."

She huffed in annoyance. With rules like that, it was a miracle if they were ever going to make any progress.

"How will I even get that clearance without knowing the basics? And how do you expect me to make any practical suggestions without a theoretical understanding?"

"Transfiguration masters come up with applications all the time, without knowing the first bit about chemistry," he pointed out. "What you ask simply isn't know at present."

"Seriously?"

He smirked. "Oh yes. I know a bit about science – my parents and brother were Muggles – but magic isn't like that. We understand the surface rules of magical systems like transfiguration, no more. You can do a lot, merely knowing how something works, not why it works."

"But... if you knew about atoms, why didn't you ever –"

"Money," he shrugged. "Basic knowledge of physics and chemistry isn't that helpful. They can help you predict the stability of the result of a transfiguration, but to answer the kinds of questions you asked would require at least a partial university education, and a number of extremely expensive experiments. And I think you will find that in the magical world, the money is with the pureblood Houses, who tend not to be inclined to invest in research using Muggle ideas, especially when it's questionable whether the results would make a profit."

That sounded remarkably familiar, at least, save for the blatantness of the bigotry. "I'll put the theoretical questions on hold – for now. Just for practical applications then..." Despite the annoyance, she had seen a few crucial breaches of the laws of physics that could surely be exploited. "Can you use transfigured things before they turn back? Like... like transfiguring a well-fed mouse, and having it run in a wheel?"

Master Blake nodded. "I can't see why that would be a problem."

"And if you attach a dynamo to the wheel? The generated energy would be non-magical... right?"

There was a pause.

"I believe so," the wizard said finally. "There would have to be extensive testing, and I would set at least the fifth degree of caution, but that idea might just work. I take it you're not thinking of actual mice?"

"No, that was just an example. If magic can violate conservation of energy, there are more effective methods. Like, can we directly create a battery to move that wheel? Or even better, what if you transfigure uranium, and use the nuclear energy to generate magic-free energy? We might just transition to completely sustainable energy overnight! And once the transfiguration wears off, you might even avoid nuclear waste – although I guess that gets into my theoretical question again." She paused. "Are you okay?"

Master Blake had blanched. "That's... I..." He took several deep breaths, then drew himself up into a rigid pose.

"On my authority as a Transfiguration Master, I must ask you to keep this idea quiet," he spoke, his tone suddenly firm. "Don't breathe a word of it to anyone but recognized authorities. Don't even write it down in your diary, or anywhere else that someone might find it. Is that acceptable?"

"Wha–" She stopped, suddenly noticing that a wand had appeared in his hand and his face was grim. The man had seemed genial, but she was suddenly very aware that the one-researcher-at-a-time setup had placed her, alone and unarmed, in a room that had been warded against eavesdropping, with a man who had the power to do anything to her, and make her forget it even happened.

She carefully refrained from making any threatening movements, and turned her voice calm and polite. "Why?"

The Transfiguration Master relaxed a little. "Because what you propose is extremely dangerous, and yet very profitable. Profitable enough that I fear that, if this idea came out, someone would try it without the adequate precautions – especially since most Transfiguration Masters are not Muggleborns, and might be misled about the nature of splitting atoms. I'm not proposing to sink your idea; you're right, it is worth finding out whether this can be done, and others might come up with the same idea. I promise that, if the Muggle government pays for it, we'll do those experiments. But we'll first need some experts from both worlds to design them, and it's going to require the absolute highest degree of caution. A warded area in the desert with all possible protections magic can build is probably not going to be enough, but if we can get away from earth –"

Madelaine just stared at him. He looked less intimidating now, but positively insane. "Aren't you exaggerating a little?"

"No," he said simply. "I believe it is you who is underestimating the risks. Which is why I set those rules. I need you to take this very seriously."

"But splitting atoms isn't that dangerous," she explained. "We've done it in the lab, when technology wasn't anywhere near as good as it is now. Even major tests of fully developed nuclear weapons don't use that kind of caution."

"Nuclear physics might not be all that dangerous," he conceded. "Transfiguration, however, is."

She could only stare.

"Did you think I was just being careful to frustrate you?" He asked softly.

It was hard to find her voice. "You teach this to children."

"Learning the skill young maximizes your potential," he shrugged helplessly. "So if we didn't teach the children, some of them would find a way to learn regardless. By giving them proper instruction instead, they at least learn the techniques along with the right way to think about them. More advanced techniques are only taught at N.E.W.T. level to those who have proved themselves on the easier material, and are either left out of books or buried in jargon. And then, of course, most people who foolishly dabble without true understanding tend to get themselves killed quickly. It takes an intelligent dabbler to cause true devastation, and those can usually be taught the wisdom to refrain. At least, with a competent teacher."

There was silence for a while, as she parsed the implications.

"You have my word," she promised eventually. "But let me get this straight. For all that transfiguration is accessible to every kid with a wand, it is strictly more dangerous than nuclear physics and completely not understood on a theoretical level – so you can't even make solid predictions about it, which only exacerbates the danger."

"Correct. Are you starting to wish for the return of witch burnings yet?"

"Oh no, I'm starting to get excited. I really want to study the theory now. But I suspect that, if this is the safety standard I should keep in mind, it's going to take years before we will get to do those nuclear experiments."

The wizard only nodded.

"So in the short term, we might want to stick to less sophisticated variations of the running mouse theme... maybe a flywheel? Or..." She stared into space, If the magical energy required to transfigure items only depended on the source and target size...

"Can you transfigure against gravity?"

Chapter 6: First Witch on the Moon

With one small step – that was also, in its own way, a giant leap – Aurora Sinistra became the first witch on the moon.

Experiment 1: success. I can still function, and I still feel my magic.

She looked out at the stars, so much easier to see here than from earth, and she looked at the beautiful vision of the earth itself. She had seen it through the rocket's window, but it was even better in the flesh. Still, her time here was costly. Perhaps if Granger's mission could be approved, she would be able to come and back and walk – or bounce, for that matter – around at her leisure.

Tom, the Muggle astronaut who'd left the rocket after her, passed her the plastic box. Carefully, very carefully, she opened it, revealing a set of squirming creatures. Flobberworms: utterly boring creatures which, however, functioned on magic rather than oxygen, which made them so useful in various potions. Flobberworms could survive in extreme environmental circumstances and, indeed, seemed perfectly fine in the less-than-comfortable conditions of the moon. She quickly closed the box again to avoid any of the creatures escaping and contaminating the biosphere; Tom took it from her hands.

Experiment 2: success. Magical creatures still seem to function.

This was crucial; the scientists had suggested that perhaps with the moon's gravity being lower, its magical field may be affected, which could have disastrous consequences for phoenixes. But now, it seemed unlikely to be a problem. The overly-careful Muggles in the space agency probably still wouldn't allow young Miss Granger to phoenix-travel here, but they might be prepared to ask one of the adult phoenix owners to take the risk. That, or the next mission would involve some of the higher magical creatures, or magical races. It didn't seem likely that any House Elves or Goblins would be interested, but perhaps a centaur would be. For all the idiosyncrasies of their culture – their inclination towards isolation, their tendency to speak in mysteries – she suspected that members of the race of stargazers would love to be here.

But that was for later. She pressed a button on her suit, and her wand dropped into her hand. She waved it in the movements she had carefully practiced, compensating for the bulkiness of the suit with just the right twitches. "Lumos!"

Nothing happened.

Aurora looked at her wand, her heart beating rapidly. It can't be. She couldn't just have failed that, could she? Quickly, she tried again.

"Lumos!"

Once more, the spell didn't take. But surely she hadn't been turned into a Muggle – no, she could still feel her magic. But – now that she realized it – the magic wasn't flowing into her wand as it usually would.

Like a dead stick in her hand.

No. No, that still wasn't right. It wasn't a dead stick; she did feel the connection... but it was different, weaker. And her magic didn't respond to her words and movements at all. Was this how a Squib would feel?

She controlled her breathing. It had to be just the location. Apparently those Muggles were wiser than she knew when they designed these experiments. There was no way it had affected her magical core permanently. Perhaps it had broken the wand, or maybe spells didn't work, but this was not going to be permanent. There was absolutely no reason to believe that it was, especially since her magic felt exactly as it always had. She was just caught up in the standard pureblood rhetoric. But still...

Experiment 3: failure. Spellcasting does not work.

She really wanted to get back to earth now, to see whether it was true, that she really hadn't lost anything, but there were two more experiments she had to do. She bit down on the little potion sack in her mouth, and felt the taste of the Draught of Peace on her tongue. Immediately she became calmer and felt the characteristic warm touch on her mind. It wasn't much, because she hadn't been expected to actually need the potion, but it helped. And it was a good sign, too.

Experiment 4: success. Potions still seem to work.

Time for the last experiment, magical artifacts. Tom was already holding out the pack of self-shuffling cards to her. He should be able to test this himself, but they had all agreed that only the magical person would interact directly with magic on this trip, to limit the risks to the other astronauts. She carefully took the cards out of the pack, and made the movement to initiate the shuffling. Again, absolutely nothing happened. It would seem like neither spells nor artifacts could be used away from the earth.

Well damn.

Chapter 12: The Good

October 1992.

"Good morning, Mr. Kaiton."

"Good morning, Madam Healer."

"You sound quite cheerful," the woman smiled. "Did you sleep well?"

"Not at all," he beamed. "It was absolute, horrendous torture for hours on end. Even worse than regrowing the tissue yesterday." He carefully wiggled his fingers. "Seems to have worked though."

"You know, my usual patients aren't quite so happy about taking Skelegro."

"Yeah, well, they're wizards, ain't they?" She nodded. "They take it for granted. Me, I've had to do without my right arm for five years. I never thought I'd get it back. That's... I'll take all the pain you can dish out for that. Do you have any idea just how many things need two hands?"

"Quite a few, I imagine." She gave him a long look. "I never really thought about it that way, but I suppose it must be a very different experience for Muggles who never realized that a cure existed."

"Totally. But you know, even knowing about magic, it wasn't like I could hope to get it. There's nowhere near enough magic to cure everyone, and me, I'm just a ex-metal worker living on benefits, there's no way I could afford to pay for this! I wouldn't have had a chance if it weren't for the NHS lottery. And with that, not one in a thousand people like me end up getting help. I'd be an absolute prat to be ungrateful for any of this."

"I see your point. But for a happy thought, problems like yours are going to be a lot more rare in the future." She smiled as she started running her wand over his arm. "It takes a relatively high effort to regrow limbs – at least for Muggles where the potions need to be guided along – but it's the work of a few minutes to stop them from getting amputated in the first place, if all that's wrong is something like a squashed arm. A number of people are working on an initiative to enable Muggle Healers to inform available Magic Healers for specific high-urgency issues. We're using the trial run as a training tool for Healers, actually. Even a first-year apprentice can handle many of the emergency room problems that typically get Muggles killed or handicapped."

"I hadn't heard about it..." Peter smiled contently. That sort of precaution would definitely have helped him. Yes, the world was getting better by the day.